John Dillenberger Papers
John Dillenberger Papers
- Writings
  - Books
    - Contours of Faith: Changing Forms of Christian Thought
      - Draft E, photocopy of typescript of what appears to be Draft D; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Galley proof (Box 10)
      - Publisher proof (Box 9)
    - John Calvin: Selections from his Writings
      - Rough draft, partial, combination of handwritten pages with cut-out photocopies; 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Draft, introduction "The Man and His Life", typescript with holograph corrections (Box 9)
      - Draft, end matter, Selected Bibliography, Indexes of names and subjects; typescript with holograph corrections (Box 9)
      - Draft, complete, combination of typescript and cut-out photocopied pages, photocopies, some with holographic corrections, pp. 1-170; 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Draft, complete, combination of typescript and cut-out photocopied pages, photocopies, some with holographic corrections; 7 folders (Box 11)
      - Draft, miscellaneous pages, photocopies from published edition, showing some corrections (Box 11)
      - Production records (Box 11)
      - Galley proof A (Box 10)
      - Galley proof B (Box 10)
      - Galley proof C (Box 12)
      - Galley proof, miscellaneous pages (Box L 12)
  - Dissertation, PhD, Columbia University, circa 1948
    - "The Hidden God: A study of the concept of the hidden God in recent German theological works and the significance of this concept for contemporary theological thinking", pp. 1-268; 4 folders (Box 11)
    - "The Hidden God: A study of the concept of the hidden God in recent German theological works and the significance of this concept for contemporary theological thinking", pp. 269-233 (Box 13)
  - Forewords
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Speeches, sermons, and addresses
    - Art and Architecture in the Religious Community, May 1, 1980; 41st National Interfaith Conference on Religion, Art, and Architecture; photocopy of typescript (Box 13)
    - "Autobiography", Nov 1968; West Coast Theological Society; photocopy of corrected typescript (Box 13)
    - Barnett Newman's Significance for Religion and the Visual Arts, Feb 15, 1980; Creatio et Spiritus Award Dinner honoring Barnett Newman, St. Peter's Church, New York; 2 copies, photocopy of typescript (Box 13)
    - "Brown Chapel", Oct 19, 1955; typescript, 2 copies (Box 13)
    - Changing Contours of Faith, Oct 23, 1964; inaugural address, San Francisco Theological Seminary; typescript (Box 13)
    - Die Bildenden Kunst und die Kirchen in der Vereinigten Staaten Ein Zweideutige aber Hoffungsvolle Weg, Aug 24, 1993; lecture, Dresden; typescript in German (Box 13)
    - "Dominican Priory", Oct 12, 1966; dinner speech, Berkeley Priory opening; typescript,, program, address of the Dominican Master General, clipping (Box 13)
    - Dürer and Cranach the Elder, Dec 1993; Sixteenth-Century Studies Conference; photocopy of corrected typescript (Box 13)
    - Educational Gyrations, May 21, 1965; American Baptist Convention; photocopy of typescript with handwritten notes (Box 13)
    - God's Omnipotent Risk, Jan 14, 1962; sermon, University Chapel of Pennsylvania State University; printed booklet with foreword (Box 13)
    - The Grandeur of Humanity: the Lure of Ideal Form in Classical Greece, the Renaissance, and Abstract Expressionism, Nov 20, 1988; American Academy of Religion, Arts Religion and Literature Section; 2 typescript copes (Box 13)
    - [Hartford Seminary], 1980; 1983; three addresses: address to Board of Directors, Dec 10, 1980 (photocopied typescript); address to Board of Trustees, May 10, 1983 (photocopied typescript); "Morning at the Seminary" worship service on Mar 23, 1983 (typescript with handwritten corrections) (Box 13)
    - Hermeneutical Orientations, Nov 22-23, 1963; Pacific Coast Theological Group (Box 13)
    - Luther and the Communication of Christianity to Culture, circa 1947 (Box 13)
    - Martin Luther: a man for no seasons, 1983; Sunstone symposium; typescript with handwritten correction, photocopy of speech delivered at the conference, correspondence with Sunstone Foundation (Box 13)
    - "Meeting of Theologians", Feb 15-16, 1963 (Box 13)
    - Mystery and the Dynamics of Historical Change, Jun 5, 1966; Commencement address, University of San Francisco; typescript with handwritten corrections, 2 official releases of text (Box 13)
    - National Jewish Chautauqua Society, May 3, 1980; two typescript copies (Box 13)
    - The Nature of Science and Cultural-Theological Concerns, undated; typescript speech with numerous handwritten corrections (Box 13)
    - One Faith, Oct 18-21, 1965; Second Pacific Northwest Faith and Order Conference; typescript (Box 13)
    - A Protestant Understanding of Church and University, June 1962; "...A condensation of three lectures given before the Council of Protestant Colleges and Universities"; photocopy of corrected typescript (Box 13)
    - Religion and the Sensibilities of the Artist, May 28, 1978; Fourth International Congress on Religion, the Arts, Architecture and the Environment, Trinity College [Trinity University?], San Antonio, TX; 2 photocopies of typescript (Box 13)
    - Rich and Poor in Spirit, Sep 28, 1980; sermon, Westminster Presbyterian Church, West Hartford, CT; 2 photocopies of typescript (Box 13)
    - The Role of Religion in the Church in Moral, Ethical Values, Sep 26-30, 1965; Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies; 2 typescript copies, one with handwritten corrections (Box 13)
    - [St. Albert's], Jun 5, 1964; commencement address; typescript (Box 13)
    - Science and Theology: Thoughts on Their Intersection, May 21, 1966; Ripon College; photocopy of corrected typescript (Box 13)
    - Spirit and the Depth of God and Man, Feb 2, 1964; sermon, Schwab Auditorium, Pennsylvania State University; typescript (Box 13)
    - Stanley Memorial Church, May 16, 1982; 2 photocopies of typescript (Box 13)
    - [Tillich address, ARC], undated (Box 13)
    - Theological-Cultural Factors Demanding Union of the Churches, undated; Commission on Church Union; typescript (Box 13)
    - A Theological Orientation to the Contemporary Church-State Setting, Jan 4-5, 1963; Commission on Church and State; typescript (Box 13)
    - Theology, Education, and Life Styles, 1971; Niebuhr Lecture Series, Elmhurst College, Elmhurst, IL (Jan 7) and Stanford Alumni College (Aug 1); three slightly different typescripts, one heavily corrected (Box 13)
    - Transcendent and Secular Claims: A Perspective on the Ministry in this Day, Jun 4, 1964; commencement address, Church Divinity School of the Pacific; photocopy of typescript (Box 13)
    - Unraveling the Library Mystique, Jun 1980; unidentified occasion, Denver, Colorado; photocopy of typescript (Box 14)
    - A Vision and Program for Hartford Seminary, Academic Programs Committee; typescript photocopy with handwritten draft pages (Box 14)
    - The Visual and the Verbal; One Reality, Two Modalities, Sep 13, 1989; Religion and the Arts, Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, Louisville, KY; 2 typescript copies, 1 with handwritten corrections (Box 14)
    - The Visual Arts and the Church in the United States: Ambiguous but Hopeful Directions, Aug 23, 1993; lecture, Dresden, Germany; photocopy of typescript (Box 14)
    - The Visual Arts, Religion and Religious Institutions, Jun 13, 1989; joint address by John and Jane, Tate Gallery, London; photocopy of typescript (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous, drafts, fragments, and notes; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Notes", late 1970's to early 1980's; appears to be mostly related to the Hartford Seminary Foundation (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous drafts, fragments, circa 1969-1970; typescript, handwritten, many relating to the Graduate Theological Union; 4 folders (Box 14)
- Writings by others
  - Tillich, Paul / Systematic Theology
    - Draft A, pp. 1-183, including table of contents; handwritten with revisions; 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Draft A [cont.], pp. 184-1097; handwritten with revisions; 13 folders (Box 15)
    - Draft A [cont.], pp. 1098-p. 1300; handwritten with revisions; 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Draft fragments, holographs, typescripts, both original reproduction, with annotations and revisions (Box 16)
- Memorabilia
  - Address by Cleve Gray, on the dedication of liturgical vestments he designed for St. James Parish, Farmington, CT; includes program of the liturgy (Box 16)
  - Administrative records, 1969-1970; proposed budget of urban-black studies center; notes on administrative matters (Box 16)
  - Calendar books, 1950-1954; 1962-1982; 25 volumes (Box 17)
  - Clippings
    - Reviews of Dillenberger's books
      - Contours of Faith (Box 16)
      - God Hidden and Revealed (Box 16)
      - Martin Luther: Selections from his Writings (Box 16)
      - Protestant Christianity (Box 16)
      - Protestant Thought and Natural Science (Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous books (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous
      - "Publicity" (Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Desk calendars, undated pages, many with handwritten number in upper right corner; 4 folders (Box 18)
  - Diploma, Columbia University PhD, 1948 (Box 18)
  - Events, 1943; 1949,; 1955,; 1957,; 1962-1968; events attended by Dillenberger, as either speaker, conference attendee, or other; includes conferences, seminars, inaugurations, convocations, commencements, worship services, etc.; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Events, 1970-1993; undated; events attended by Dillenberger, as either speaker, conference attendee, or other; includes conferences, seminars, inaugurations, convocations, commencements, worship services, etc.; 4 folders (Box 19)
  - Honoraria, citations and addresses given for honorary degrees, certificate of appreciation, honorary degrees, etc.; 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Jane Dillenberger, articles and speeches by (Box 19)
  - List of speeches, covers 1963-1966 (Box 19)
  - Naval records, 1949-1950; includes discharge papers from U.S. Naval Reserve (Box 19)
  - Pastor's Manual, 1943; from Dillenberger's time as Chaplain in the US Naval Reserves; stamped, date and name embossed on cover in gold (Box 19)
  - Printed material
    - Articles about or mentioning Dillenberger (Box 19)
    - Articles about or mentioning Dillenberger, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Graduate Theological Union course catalog, 1968-1969 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Publisher advertising for Dillenberger's books (Box 16)